When you are sick and cannot work because of the disease
as an employee, you should make a sickness report directly to your employer.
The employer is responsible for sick pay
the first 14 days of the sick period.
Anyone who is not employed but instead is self -employed,
unemployed or parental sick leave to report directly to the Social Insurance Office
and then apply for sickness benefit.
At the beginning of the sick period, a waiting deduction is made.
For employees it is deducted from sick pay by the employer and for others from the sickness benefit
by the Social Insurance Office.
From day eight of the sick period
The certificate should describe what disease the person has and on
which way it is limiting and how the doctor has arrived at it.
For employees with
sick pay and self -employed we make the assessment based on the
The so -called rehabilitation chain, which is part of the Social Security Code.
Here are fixed time frames for assessing work ability.
The longer the sick leave is in progress
The more the assessment is widened.
The purpose of the rehabilitation chain is to take advantage of it
Work ability The individual has and, if necessary, promotes transition.
This assumes that the Swedish Social Insurance Agency together with other actors
Make a decision on sickness benefit.
The Swedish Social Insurance Agency may need to supplement the decision basis with clarifications
or further information.
Even the one who does not work when
The need for sick leave arises can be granted sickness benefit.
Anyone who is unemployed is judged directly in relation to normal
existing work in the labor market.
Parental leave is assessed in relation to the ability to take care of the child.
Here, the Social Insurance Office investigates, among other things, who in that case takes care of the child
When the parent is ill and has a reduced ability to do so.
For those who study it is the study ability
the ability is impaired approved the sick period and information is sent to CSN
so that the person is allowed to retain their study support.
Usually, this means that the study ability must be fully impaired.
Anyone studying needs a medical certificate from day 15.
In the cases that the sick person has
Various employment at the same time, the assessment is divided.
For example, the person who is is assessed
partly unemployed in relation to normal work.
For that part they are unemployed and in relation to the rehabilitation chain
for their employees.
Depending on the employment and situation of the sick leave, there may be one
several different actors who need to be involved in the person's
Rehabilitation and return to work.
All actors have different roles and responsibilities
make diagnosis and assess the need for care and treatment,
But also to decide on sick leave.
If the doctor concluded that the disease and its consequences
If the work ability puts down it should be described in the medical certificate.
The Employment Service is responsible for support to
The one as unemployed, but also support for transition.
If a person who employed cannot go back to work with his employer.
This includes being responsible for the individual's work -oriented rehabilitation.
The municipality is responsible for social efforts
and support to plan for self -sufficiency.
The Swedish Social Insurance Agency is responsible for investigating and assessing the work capacity
It may also be the case that the work capacity is no longer impaired
Due to illness, but that the need for rehabilitation remains.
In order for preventive sickness benefit to be granted, one must just as for
Sickness benefit is both insured in Sweden and have a sickness benefit -based income, SGI.
The purpose of compensation is to prevent,
shorten or cancel a reduction in work capacity.
This means that it can be granted if the person, for example, has
or risks developing a disease that can lead to reduced work capacity.
The medical treatment or rehabilitation
shall be prescribed by a doctor and even included in a
The Försäkringskassan approved plan for the person to be granted the compensation.